Finding Aid for Elizabeth Caroline Crosby Papers 1888-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Research (Crosby)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Hypothalamus" (Box 5)
  - Course Material
    - "Phylogenetic Development of the Nervous System of Vertebrates" (Box 6)
  - Neuroanatomical Illustrations, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Laboratory Methods and Stains (Box 6)
  - Lab Notebooks circa 1920s (Box 6)
  - Experimental Results circa 1918
    - "Autotransplants" (Box 6)
    - "Degenerated Heterotransplants" (Box 6)
    - "Injections of absolute alcohol to prevent neuroma formation" (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 6)
- Conferences
  The Conferences series consists of materials donated in 1982 documenting Crosby's participation or attendance at a wide variety of mediacal conferences. The series is arranged chronologically and thereafter by the name of the sponsoring organization (when known). If this is not known, then the name of the conference is listed.
  - 1939
    - Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Diseases (Box 4)
  - 1953
    - Melon Lecture (Box 4)
  - 1958
    - C.U. Ariens Kappers Speech (Box 4)
  - 1959
    - Dutch Central Institute for Brain Research (Box 4)
  - 1961
    - Symposium on Oculomotor System (Box 4)
  - 1962
    - International Meeting of Neurobiologists (Box 4)
  - 1963
    - The Neurological Society of America and the Society of British Neurological Surgeons (Box 4)
  - 1965
    - Illinois College of Medicine (Box 4)
    - The Japan Society of Vestibular Research (Box 4)
    - Phylogenesis and Ontogenesis of the Forebrain (Box 4)
  - 1966
    - International Meeting of Neurobiologists (Box 4)
    - Medical College of Georgia (Box 4)
  - 1967
    - Societe Francaise de Neurologie (Box 4)
  - 1968
    - American Association of Neuropathologists (Box 4)
    - American Philosophical Society (Box 4)
    - Neuroscience Symposium in the Southwest (Box 4)
    - Societe Francaise de la Neurologie (Box 4)
  - 1969
    - American Medical Association (Box 4)
    - Central Neurological Society (Box 4)
    - Congressus Morphologicus (Box 4)
    - Pan American Congress of Anatomy (Box 4)
    - Southern Society of Anatomists (Box 4)
  - 1970
    - American Society for Neurochemistry (Box 4)
    - International Congress of Neuropathology (Box 4)
  - 1971
    - American Association of Neuropathologists (Box 4)
  - 1972
    - Pan American Congress of Anatomy (Box 4)
    - Second International Symposium on Motor Control (Box 4)
    - Societe Francaise de Neurologie (Box 4)
  - 1973
    - University of Alabama, Neuroanatomical Research Conference (Box 4)
      (also material for 1974 and 1978 conferences)
  - 1975
    - Fulton Society Symposium (Box 4)
  - 1977
    - American Neurological Association (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Lectures
  The Lectures series consists of materials donated in 1982 related to lectures Crosby presented around the world. The series is arranged chronologically and includes a "Miscellaneous" folder of undated and untitled lectures.
  - 1949
    - Peet Lecture (Box 4)
  - 1965
    - Bangkok, Thailand (Box 4)
  - 1970
    - Allan A. Bailey Memorial Lecture (Box 4)
  - Undated
    - R. McColler Lectures on Gross Anatomy (Box 4)
    - University of Alabama Distinguished Faculty Lecture (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Lectures (Box 4)
- Organizations
  The Organizations series consists of materials donated in 1982 documenting Crosby's membership in a variety of organizations. The series is arranged alphabetically by organization name.
  - Alabama Academy of Science (Box 4)
  - American Association of Neuropathologists (Box 4)
  - Anatomical associations miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Cajal Club (Box 4)
  - Comparative Neurology Group (Box 4)
  - Harvey Cushing Society (Box 4)
  - International Brain Research Organization (Box 4)
  - International Society of Psychoneuroendocrinology (Box 4)
  - Los Angeles Foundation of Otology (Box 4)
  - Society for Neuroscience (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains a rich and extensive collection of photographs, covering virtually every phase of Crosby's life, collected by Schneider probably to serve as illustrations for his biography. Included are photographic portraits of Crosby's parents, of Crosby as a child and a young adult, and at various phases throughout her professional career; photographs of her hometown of Petersburg, Michigan dating from the turn of the century; Crosby's sabbatical in Scotland (1939-1940); the Symposium on Phylogenesis and Ontogenesis of the Forebrain (1965) of which Crosby was the president; shots of Crosby "in action" either conducting research or teaching classes; group photographs of Crosby with colleagues at various points in her career; Crosby receiving some of her numerous awards and honors, most notably her acceptance of the National Medal of Science from President Carter in 1980; and portraits of colleagues and mentors who were influential in Crosby's professional development. As with most of the other materials in the Crosby collection, these photographs focus almost exclusively (with the exception of the family and childhood photos) upon Crosby's professional career and provide little insight into her personal life.
  - Family and Childhood Portraits (Box 6)
  - Hometown of Petersburg, Mich circa 1890-1920 (Box 6)
  - Portraits (Box 6)
  - Sabbatical in Scotland circa 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Symposium on Phylogenesis and Ontogenesis of the Forebrain: Frankfurt, Germany 1965 (Box 6)
  - Research and Experimentation (Box 6)
  - Teaching (Box 6)
  - Group Photographs with Colleagues (Box 6)
  - Receptions and Awards Ceremonies (Box 6)
  - Influential Colleagues and Mentors: Ariens, Kappers, Herrick, Huber, Lockhardt (Box 6)
- Audiovisual Materials
  The Audiovisual Materials series provides an interesting mix of information resources which supplement and further elucidate the other major series included in the 1994 accession. The audio cassette recordings of oral interviews of Dr. Crosby, and of her friend and colleague, Isabelle Lockhard,(conducted by Schneider) provide some evidence of Crosby's personality not often revealed in other sources of the Biographical Materials series. Also, the recording of an interview of Crosby by WUOM (a campus radio station) represents perhaps the only instance in the collection in which Crosby, in her own words, describes how she viewed her role as a woman in a male-dominated field and her opinions regarding how much gender discrimination she may have faced. Similarly, an audio recording (3 cassettes) of a classroom lecture conducted by Crosby in 1955 offers the only real evidence in the collection of Crosby's vaunted teaching ability. The video tapes included in this series serve to further elucidate the Research series by capturing Crosby in action in the latter phase of her career conducting clinical experiments. Also included is a video tape of the award ceremony in which Crosby received the National Medal of Science from President Carter in 1980.
  - Audio Cassettes
    - Interview of Dr. Crosby by Richard C. Schneider (Box 7)
    - Interview of Dr. Isabelle Lockhard about Dr. Crosby 02/01/1985 (Box 7)
      (by Richard C. Schneider)
    - Recording of "Crosby Memoir" aired 1/3/1984 on Research News radio program, WUOM (Box 7)
    - Dr. Crosby Seminar 11/03/1955, 3 audiocassettes (Box 7)
  - Video Tapes
    - Presidential Ceremony Honoring the 1979 Medal of Science Awardees, White House, 01/14/1980, U-Matic, approx. 20 min. (Box 7)
    - Torsional and Somersaulting Movements from Vestibular Cortex Mediated through the Insula, Richard C. Schneider, Elizabeth C. Crosby, Hazel D. Calhoun, U-Matic, 5 min., 40 sec. (Box 7)
    - Crosby, Vestibular Otology 05/14/1980, 5 videotapes U-matic (Box 7)
    - Crosby, Vestibular Otology 05/15/1980, 3 videotapes U-matic